Guide to the New-York Historical Society Management Committee Records 1804-1938 NYHS-RG 1
New-York Historical Society
- Series IV. Official Papers, 1805-1938; 10.6 Linear feet
  - Official Papers. 1910 (2 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Includes the memorials of Henry Dexter, John Austin Stevens, and Richard Schieffelin.
  - Official Papers. 1911. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Includes an extract from two deeds of gift to the Beekman Family Association that refer to contingencies by which N-YHS would take title to the gifts. Includes a draft resolution accepting relics from the Beekman House, including the family coach. Includes an insurance certificate covering transit to the Hotel Astor for one day of the painting Return of the 69th Regiment.
  - Official Papers. 1912 (1 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 6)
    Includes the memorial of the sister and daughter of N-YHS president Samuel Hoffman, provenance information about a silver key inscribed to John S. Giles donated to N-YHS by Giles's grandson, the remarks of N-YHS delegate James Benedict at the dedication of the New York State Education Building, and the N-YHS petition to the U.S. House of Representatives to erect a National Archives building.
  - Official Papers. 1912 (2 of 2). George C. Dodd Matter., 1910-1912 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    Includes documents related to the dispute between N-YHS and photographer George C. Dodd over ownership of slides and negatives taken by Dodd. These documents include the agreement resolving the matter and detailed lists of the items at issue.
  - Official Papers. 1913 (1 of 2)., 1902-1903, 1913 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    Includes a print copy of the Executive Committee rules for 1913 and documents related to N-YHS's historical interest in New York State preserving its official records. This last includes material from 1902-1903.
  - Official Papers. 1913 (2 of 2). Proposed By-Law Revisions. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    Includes documents related to the by-law revisions proposed by the Special Committee formed for that purpose,
  - Official Papers. 1914. (Box 19, Folder 10)
    Includes resolutions concerning the sale to Patrick Burns of N-YHS's interest in a real estate lot at 63rd St. and 2nd Ave. and concerning N-YHS's consent to a matter related to the Beekman Family Association. Includes a pamphlet Don'ts: An Ounce of Prevention is Worth a Pound of Cure issued by The Employer's Liability Assurance Corporation of London, England.
  - Official Papers. 1915 (1 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Official Papers. 1915 (2 of 2). Special Committee on the City Flag. (Box 19, Folder 12)
    Includes the report of the committee and other documents concerning the proposed design for a New York City flag.
  - Official Papers. 1916 (1 of 2). (Box 19, Folder 13)
    Includes a proposed appeal, not acted on, for funds to expand the Central Park West building, two Finance Committee reports concerning investments, and a report of the Committee on the Audubon Memorial Exhibition.
  - Official Papers. 1916 (2 of 2). Abbott Egyptian Collection Preservation. (Box 19, Folder 14)
    Includes documents related to concerns about the condition of the Egyptian collection and opposition by some within N-YHS to any consideration of transferring the collection to a museum, specifically the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
  - Official Papers. 1917 (1 of 8). (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1917 (2 of 8). (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1917 (3 of 8). Special Committee., 1900, 1917, 1919 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    This folder and the next include documents concerning the Special Committee formed in January 1917 to consider the resolutions offered by member Mrs. John Van Rensselaer, a critic of N-YHS's direction. This folder includes correspondence from the American Antiquarian Society, Historical Society of Pennsylvania, and others regarding Van Rensselaer's criticisms. The folder includes a letter from 1900 that relates to a specific criticism, and a 1919 letter that reflects back on one aspect of the committee's work.
  - Official Papers. 1917 (4 of 8). Special Committee., 1917 February (Box 20, Folder 4)
    Includes the manuscript and print versions of the Special Committee's report, as approved at the February 6, 1917, Society meeting, with a typescript of the meeting's proceedings.
  - Official Papers. 1917 (5 of 8). Report of the Committee to Revise the By-Laws., 1917 November (Box 20, Folder 5)
    Includes the manuscript and print versions of the report submitted to the Society meeting of November 13.
  - Official Papers. 1917 (6 of 8). Society Meeting to Take Action on the Report of the Committee to Revise the By-Laws., 1917 December (Box 20, Folder 6)
    Includes copies of the transcript of the debate over the by-laws revision, which was passed.
  - Official Papers. 1917 (7 of 8). Proxies., 1917 January-February (Box 20, Folder 7)
    Includes the forms returned by N-YHS members empowering J. Archibald Murray, Frederic D. Weekes, and R. Horace Gallatin, representing the Board of Officers, to vote as their proxy on any matter during 1917. The folder includes one of the form letters communicating the proxy form to the members.
  - Official Papers. 1917 (8 of 8). Proxies., 1916-1917 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    Includes a copy of the Charter, By-Laws, Officers, Members, Report of the Executive Committee of 1916, with the list of members annotated, apparently in connection with proxies.
  - Official Papers. 1918 (1 of 2). (Box 21, Folder 1)
    Includes the memorials of Fancher Nicoll (killed in action in WWI) and of Gerard Beekman, drafts of appeals for funds for the Egyptian collection and expansion of the Central Park West building, and a report on a problem with the building's steam heating infrastructure.
  - Official Papers. 1918 (2 of 2). Membership Matters. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1919 (1 of 3). (Box 21, Folder 3)
    Includes the report of the committee recommending against the loan of the Jarvis Indian objects to the Museum of the American Indian, the report of the Art Committee recommending the acceptance of the portrait of Robert Murray, and the recommendations of the Committee on Plan & Scope.
  - Official Papers. 1919 (2 of 3). Membership Matters. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Official Papers. 1919 (3 of 3). Circulars., 1919 November-December (Box 21, Folder 5)
    Includes documents concerning dissident membership charges of mismanagement and the proxy and circular mailings in advance of the January 1920 election of N-YHS officers. Documents include the N-YHS circulars of December 5 and December 16 responding to the charges, the December 9 statement of the dissidents, the proxy form mailing, and the slate of officers proposed by the Nominating Committee, among other items.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (1 of 11). Annual Meeting Typescript., 1920 January 6 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    Includes typescript of the proceedings of the Society meeting of January 6.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (2 of 11). Election Results., 1920 January (Box 21, Folder 7)
    Includes the petition of the opposition with their slate of nominees, the regular and opposition tickets, certification of the election inspectors, and other documents.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (3 of 11). Clippings., 1920 January (Box 21, Folder 8)
    Includes clippings and transcriptions of press coverage surrounding the January N-YHS meeting and election.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (4 of 11). Proxy Work Files., 1920 January (Box 21, Folder 9)
    This file and the next three appear to be the workpapers related to the recording of returned proxy votes.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (5 of 11). Proxy Work Files., 1920 January (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Official Papers. 1920 (6 of 11). Proxy Work Files., 1920 January (Box 21, Folder 11)
    Includes a copy of the Annual Report, By-Laws and List of Members of 1919 (for year 1918), with annotations on the member list indicating those in opposition to the management slate.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (7 of 11). Proxy Work Files., 1920 January (Box 21, Folder 12)
    Includes the opposition proxies received and some duplicate regular ticket proxies.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (8 of 11). Regular Ticket Proxies., 1919 December-1920 January (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1920 (9 of 11). Mrs. Van Rensselaer Communications., 1920, 1925 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    Includes Mrs. Van Rensselaer's communications of February (subsequent to the defeat of her opposition slate in January) to Stuyvesant Fish and the N-YHS Executive Committee, and the October report of the committee formed to consider those communications. A 1925 notice of Van Rensselaer's death is in the file.
  - Official Papers. 1920 (10 of 11). General Membership Matters. (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1920 (11 of 11). Other Matters. (Box 22, Folder 4)
    Includes documents related to matters of 1920 other than the January election and general membership matters.
  - Official Papers. 1921 (1 of 2). (Box 22, Folder 5)
    Includes counsel's opinion on the number of copies of publications to be printed by the DePeyster Publication Fund.
  - Official Papers. 1921 (2 of 2). Liberty Pole. (Box 22, Folder 6)
    Includes items related to the dedication of a replica of the Liberty Pole erected in City Hall Park. Items include the report of N-YHS's Liberty Pole Committee (chaired by Reginald Pelham Bolton), dedication program and tickets, and lapel pins.
  - Official Papers. 1922 (1 of 2). (Box 22, Folder 7)
    Includes the Art Committee's proposal to dispose of 98 poor quality and deteriorated paintings, principally from the Durr estate donation.
  - Official Papers. 1922 (2 of 2). Building Committee., 1922, 1924 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    Includes documents concerning the renewed initiative to raise funds to acquire additional property on 76th and 77th streets and to expand the Central Park West building.
  - Official Papers. 1923 (1 of 2). (Box 22, Folder 9)
    Includes a map by Reginald Pelham Bolton, done for the N-YHS Field Exploration Committtee, of Fort Washington and the line of the Third Line of American entrenchments (1776) along 159th-161st streets.
  - Official Papers. 1923 (2 of 2). Election of Officers., 1922-1923 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    Includes a copy of Annual Report, Charter, By-Laws, and List of Members for the year 1921, with an annotated member list indicating proxies received, and a typescript of the January 2 meeting.
  - Official Papers. 1924. (Box 22, Folder 11)
    Includes a report from Librarian Alexander Wall on his travels in Europe in the summer of 1924 on behalf of N-YHS. On this trip Wall purchased the collection of Cadwallader Colden papers in England; his report includes a summary of the collection.
  - Official Papers. 1925 (1 of 2). (Box 22, Folder 12)
    Includes resolutions and printed correspondence concerning the donation of the collections of the Naval History Society, report of the committee considering a medal to be awarded by N-YHS on occasion for meritorious work in history, and the marketing material for the publication Uniforms of the American, British, French and Hessian Armies.
  - Official Papers. 1925 (2 of 2). Building Expansion. (Box 22, Folder 13)
    Includes an outline by York & Sawyer of proposed construction and alterations to the Central Park West building, resolutions, proposed property acquisitions, correspondence, and summaries of committee activities.
  - Official Papers. 1926., 1925-1926 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    Includes January 1926 officer election documents.
  - Official Papers. 1927. (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1928. (Box 28, Folder 3)
    Includes the New York State legislative act adding "educational purposes" to the stated purposes of N-YHS.
  - Official Papers. 1929 (1 of 3). (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Official Papers. 1929 (2 of 3). Election of Officers., 1928-1929 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    Includes a copy of Annual Report and List of Members for the year 1927, with an annotated member list indicating proxies received.
  - Official Papers. 1929 (3 of 3). Proxies., 1928-1929 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1930. (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Official Papers. 1931. (Box 23, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1932 (1 of 3). (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Official Papers. 1932 (2 of 3). Election of Officers., 1931-1932 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    Includes a copy of Annual Report and List of Members for the year 1930, with an annotated member list indicating proxies received.
  - Official Papers. 1932 (3 of 3). (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Official Papers. 1933. (Box 24, Folder 4)
    Includes a draft statement read at the Executive Committee's December 19 meeting on the purposes and risks of making exhibition loans from the collection, and proposing limitations on these.
  - Official Papers. 1934. (Box 24, Folder 5)
    Includes a report from the Art Committee concerning comments they received from restorers on the condition of the Old Masters in the collection.
  - Official Papers. 1935 (1 of 3). (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Official Papers. 1935 (2 of 3). Election of Officers., 1934-1935 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    Includes a copy of Annual Report and List of Members for the year 1933, with an annotated member list indicating proxies received.
  - Official Papers. 1935 (3 of 3). (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Official Papers. 1935-1936 (Box 24, Folder 9)
    Includes documents related to an analysis of N-YHS's investments as of late 1935 with recommendations for changes to the portfolio, and related documents from 1936.
  - Official Papers. 1936 (1 of 3). (Box 24, Folder 10)
    Includes a report by Hugh M. Flick with his observations concerning efforts to obtain historical documents from private owners in rural areas; minutes of the December 2 meeting of the Plan and Scope Committee with a draft agreement for the loan of various materials to the Brooklyn Museum, including the Abbott Egyptian collection, Lenox Ninevah sculptures, Foster and Larkin Peruvian objects, and the Anderson, Smith, Norman, and American Ethnological collections, among other objects; and memorials to James Barnes and Frederic Delano Weekes.
  - Official Papers. 1936 (2 of 3). Special Meeting of the Society. (Box 24, Folder 11)
    Includes documents related to the June 16 Special Meeting of the Society called by the Executive Committee for the purpose of having the membership approve of the Committee's decision to proceed with the construction of the wings for the Central Park West building.
  - Official Papers. 1936 (3 of 3). Proxies. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    Includes two copies of Annual Report and List of Members for the year 1935, with annotated member lists indicating proxies received.
  - Official Papers. 1937 (1 of 4). (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Official Papers. 1937 (2 of 4). (Box 25, Folder 3)
    Includes Librarian Alexander Wall's report to the Executive Committee presenting his vision for N-YHS's library, museum, and other operations in the completed Central Park West building, reports of the Building Committee providing status updates on the construction, reports from the Art Committee concerning possible restoration work on paintings, and the remarks at the presentation of a distinguished service medal to George A. Zabriskie.
  - Official Papers. 1937 (3 of 4). Special Meeting of the Society. (Box 25, Folder 4)
    Includes documents related to the November 18 Special Meeting of the Society called by the Executive Committee to obtain membership approval of revised by-laws that would place governance of the Society with a Board of Trustees. Includes a copy of Annual Report and List of Members for the year 1936, with an annotated member list indicating proxies received.
  - Official Papers. 1937 (4 of 4). Proxies. (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Official Papers. 1938 (1 of 2)., 1937-1938 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    Includes an inventory of N-YHS institutional records boxed for moving.
  - Official Papers. 1938 (2 of 2). (Box 25, Folder 7)
    Includes minutes of the Art, Library, and Museum Committees. Includes credit reports on railroad companies and the Baltimore & Ohio Railroad Company debt modification plan sent to the Finance Committee by the Wall Street firm Halsted & Harrison.